this is a question on um practice for
Lay people
mhm and how should a lay person
practice if their goal is
nian or at least some stage towards it I
presume yeah because you can't attana as
a lay
person um the suas are pretty clear on
that but that doesn't mean you can't
practice the words it
right so well you would
practice in the same way the monks
do just on the basis of a greater
compromise compromise of a household
life but um the practice does not
somehow miraculously become
different because you can't leave your
home or you can't leave your family or
you have a duty towards it and then you
can do a different thing towards the
same goal of nibana no it's still the
same practice
practice
so often it can feel like a like a high
standard for a late person to
achieve like keeping the eight precepts
celibate um practice towards um the right view or
um practice towards um the right view or
maybe even non- return all of that's
possible all of that was in the suas
recorded uh but what also always does
what what those sutas would always also
say was quite clearly that
um in order for one to practice
successfully whether a monk or person he
needs to understand the Peril of
sensuality the Mind needs to be free
from hindrances on the basis of um
thorough virtue and sense restraint so
then the difference basically was only
um it wasn't in the path they were
applying themselves to the difference
was simply um on uh in the circumstance
es they were keeping them back but the
practice was the same so if it feels
like a high like a tall
order um it well it's normal it's going to
um it well it's normal it's going to
feel that way and it's fine to feel that
way but it's important to not then try
to devalue or lower the threshold oh
because just seems so unattainable so
give me something simpler no quite the
opposite if actually the goal and the
threshold remains High even your failure
to reach it will constitute more
successful practice than successfully
practicing towards a lower threshold
toward something that's not the
beginning of the dharm but you were led
to believe it
is the good example of that is this like
you know it seems to be quite I mean I
don't know how prevalent but but I think
there probably quite a few
people that uh kind of delusionally
believe you know whether through their
own doing or because they were LED
astray that you can keep the five precepts and
that you can keep the five precepts and
practice the
dhama as a as a lay person it's like no
you look at any suta whenever the Buddha
told the five precepts it was just to
get better rebirths Heavenly rebirths to
enjoy sensuality
further uh instructing the spouses you
know how to look after each other how to
be faithful because they're going to get
great sensually reward it was quite
clearly not presented as the Noble eful
Path you know the one way only towards
purification of being the saana no he
was clearly presented to those who don't
want to practice who are not interested
in practicing so it's like okay well
still if you have a degree of virtue on
the level of high precepts a degree of
honesty uh a degree of U reasoning
looking after your family I mean the
Buddha was teaching people how to spend
their money so that's what mean like it's
money so that's what mean like it's
quite delusional to believe that these
things somehow also lead you to nibana
when the context in the sutas was quite
clear however Whenever there were lay
people quite you know the foremost nand
mat the foremost in in janas Lay
woman um all the other householders they
had many disciples they were all fully
established in virtue eight precept so
the Perils of sensuality sense restraint
all of that and that's how they got
where they were and then you also had
lay people in the sutas
they were soapas or
saamis uh but they were not they were
living by five preets but that was
after after they got The Right View
because they were lucky enough to talk
to the Buddha and the Buddha to guide
them step by step uh then they went back
home and were content with that
attainment and then kept the five
precepts and remained being a good
person but they were clearly not
practicing further and when the Buddha didn't
further and when the Buddha didn't
instruct for example anapenda you know
the famous instruction before he even
started talking anything about ad dama
to him he was he first obviously the
generosity the Merit that you make
elevated mind talking about the heavens
the good rebers and then he was talking
about the Perils of sensuality the
absolute deprivation of sensual desires
the the the the bait the Trap the
suffering all of that and then he said
then he his mind was
ready to hear the dam and then he told
him D he got a Right View so if today
you were told to dhama you're not
getting the right view why is
that well cuz you're not seeing the
depth of the Perils of
sensuality and that's why it wasn't
taught generally to lay people the D for
who knows half of half of the Buddha's
life probably quite a few decades yeah
because it says in the S we do not teach
this we not teach this no because they
would leave like it's
incompatible so now obviously as I said
the people have all this access to the
sutas and so on plus let's not even get
into you know the whole idea of you can
practice meditation and meditation
techniques that somehow lead you to the
meat of the practice on the basis of
your five precepts or something there's
no such suta at all and even Sati patana
as we said before orap Sati was told to
Noble disciples or if they were just
short of noble disciples it was still
taught to the monks at least who were
fully ready for that through sense
restraint and virtue in parts of in
terms of the gradual
training so so this whole view that that
you can kind of um be a
householder keep the five precepts you
know do your best in that regard and do
your meditation technique and somehow
that constitutes your practice for dhama
just think about it like if monks who
would have given up a lot
more need to do all these other things
in terms of the Buddha's instruction you
know the detail instruction and and
repetitive and constantly having to
remind them and and a right sense of
urgency they still need to do a lot on
the basis of already having done a lot
giving up the the household the
attachments the bonds all of that but
they need to do a lot but then you have
somebody who hasn't even given all of
that up and needs to do even less for
the same practice that's simply
irrational even if you think about it
put aside that the to simply don't
support that idea just stop and think
about it surely it would be other way
around surely if somebody would not have
given up the big part of abstraction for
the holy for the for the goal of the
Holy life we need to do then even a lot
more just to compensate for that
compromise and somebody who would have
given it already up and lives already in
a higher kind
of in a higher environment of sense
restraint well they would need they
would need to do the less
so the point is if you feel disheartened
oh but it's just so much it's fine but
don't obscure the fact that it is that's
the threshold once you sort of calm down
and come to terms with it if you still
keep trying towards that which feels too
much you are actually still getting
closer to it even through your failures
so keep the five precepts and then keep
the eight precepts every now and then
but keep them really
unconditionally and don't look for
meditation techniques to to compensate
for your
intentionally chosen uh unsuitable environment but
chosen uh unsuitable environment but
take responsibility for
it and then feel the weight of that
choice feel the weight of the
compromise and through doing that you
are actually on the right track even if
you never become a monk you are still
practicing more rightly that somebody
who would have lowered the threshold
just because because the threshold they
hear make upsets
them it makes them feel bad or it it
makes them feel disheartened and they
don't want to do
anything no the threshold Remains the
Same think about if I if I
basically if there is a peak of the
mountain you have to climb
to it's not negotiable that is the
peak and if you don't aim in the
direction of that Peak because it's too
much and start walking in the opposite
direction you're not getting closer to
the peak even if you climb other other
other mountains it's not the one you
should be
climbing so the point is to recognize
that yeah it feels too high I don't even
know I can do it but at least if I don't
lower it down just to please myself my
ignorant self my aims will be aiming High where
self my aims will be aiming High where
they should and you know when you aim
high even when you fail you fail
relatively higher than you were
before and same same principle in
education or in any other field like if
you aim for for like
a higher goal or a more kind of accurate
sort of higher purpose even your failure
will be a relative success yeah there's
there's the but if I lower the the the
the threshold and tell you oh no no just
just do this well you're going to aim
even lower now you're going to fall even
lower than
that and that's the whole point so it's
it's not like all this insistence on
sens and stuff it's not just to
dishearten and oh this is just for the
monks no it's for anybody who wants to
practice the dharm and this is the
beginning of the
dama if you read the sutas you will
arrive at the very same conclusion you
don't have to take my word for it and
even like as I said n mat that I
mentioned you know she was like anagami
and she when she talked about herself
she said and she had a husband and she
had a kid
before but she said even then since she
was was a young girl when she was given
to her
husband in marriage she was never
unfaithful to him even in her
thought let alone in the body of
speech so you realize that she was
already quite a developed human being
like how many people today can say that
even mentally they don't trans regress
they don't have a thought of
sensuality so you realize she was
beautiful she bought him a kid when he
died she immediately became celibate she
was simply not interested in any of that
since way before and then when her own
son was imprisoned falsely imprisoned
falsely accused killed she didn't go and
fight the king for Injustice she said
her mind remained unchanged and then de
put the praise there like oh wow you can
purify thoughts in the manifestations as
they manifest they're already
clear so it's like yeah a lay person can
do do that and even back then that was
impressive there were monks who couldn't
do that so it's like it's not about oh
you must become a monk or a nun it's
about you mustn't lower the
threshold and then keep trying towards
that level and understand that even if
you are failing you're failing in regard
to the right direction so you are
actually going forward maybe not as fast
as you would like to or as others would
promise you but you are going forward
through that repetition of of of failure
of the right aim You Are
Climbing so some people might say that
okay well I I'm not so good with my
virtue I keep five pieces every now and
then eight pieces every now and then I
fail at
it um but I compensate that with
meditation technique meditation whatever
well you you have basically the whole
vuda commentaries the whole Abid dama to
blame for that that was a complete
invention when they Tred to
popularize uh Buddhism for
masses I think I told you I think it was
a Buddha Goa who said the the visim Maga
compiler who said he hopes that his work
will inspire people whereby even common
householders will speak about meditation
on a daily basis because it's a you know
it became quite associated with the
whole National PR religion the whole
idea of it um and so it's no wonder that
virtue had to suffer on account of it
the threshold of virtue because that's
one thing that that your average
householder doesn't want to hear doesn't
want to
do so if you love with that and present
some some more instantaneously
gratifying yogic tantric hypnotic
meditation techniques then you would get
probably quite a few followers in that
regard and ever since even the whole
like the the Thai tradition Boran Katan
and the Thai Forest meditation you look
at the history of it it just came
exactly from these epidemic views mixed
with Tibetan and Chinese Tantra and and
sort of visualization practices and
stuff and uh again intention from for
popularizing yeah exactly came from the
same Source came from the same source
and then even people with the and see
why why that's so dangerous like even
people who would have committed for
right reasons to the practice if that's
say they arve at thinking that's what
the Buddha actually taught they wouldn't
look further and they'll be doing this
nonsense instead of doing the right
thing they were perfectly capable of
doing if they were
told so the whole and same in Burma the
whole vas movement was told by that
minister to the teacher of mahashi like
King's minister or something because
again he was like he was very bound with
the with the Buddhist identity colonial
times the pressures and stuff so he was
like let's find the suta that can serve
as a basis and then created these
technique practices which by the way are
quite helpful management for people
management techniques like any other
sort of practices you might do to help
like you know relieve the stress yeah
but confusing that for the Buddhist
practice it's pretty much confusing
basically treating of a random symptom
for the illness and then when the
symptom disappears you think you cure
now while actually your your illness is
deteriorating that's why it's the most
the most perilous thing to do in that
sense you read sutas the instruction to
lay people five precepts eight precepts
when you can more often better great uh
obviously fulfill your other duties but
then at the same time reflect reflect on
the nature of Enlightenment reflect on
the Buddha the DH the S obviously it's
always presented in that way you know
through the oral transmission lots of
details were lost but you could
extrapolate from that and see well what
is what is what would be the quality is
the properties of of an enlightened mind
well it would be obviously discussed
with sensuality freedom from any any
physical Cravings freedom from conceit
so okay so all of these context all of
these ideas think about sit down for an hour
ideas think about sit down for an hour
and instead of watching your belly
rising up and down think about the
property of being free from conceit and
try and apply it on the basis of your
whatever limited virtue limited sensory
strength still work in the same
still work in the same
direction as I said the path does not
magically become different just cuz you
can't do
this it's still the same
practice pick up any other quality same
different times different Reflections
but invest time in it and then try to
apply it so when you end up in situations that
it so when you end up in situations that
provoke your conceit provoke your lust
provoke your anger Ah that's the TR
training now tame the animal in regard
to this within my compromised
environment for which I have taken up
responsibility let me so even like
that's like and that's why
it's you realize like all you can do is
say these things basically to people
because at least one in 100 when they
hear it they will be able to do it and and
it they will be able to do it and and
the reason they were able to do it is
cuz they actually heard it they were
told they can't have an excuse to say
well I was never
told because it's it's kind of like the
the whole direction of what people like
to think the practice is it's not
incidental that kind of it does go with
the general flow of of n nature kind of
preferences and so on it kind of just
tailors to that so even if as I said if
even if people were maybe misled
somebody told you this is the practice
unlighted mind will quite happily leap
onto that and proliferate further and
defend it and so on and not question it
so yes you might have been misled but if
you would have heard the other
alternative like this and still
irrationally chose this without any
questioning well now that's your own
doing so that's what I mean all you can
do is keep saying it because some people
at least when they hear it well they
can't just go back to what they were
doing before without asking certain
questions and if you start asking them
you'll see how quickly the whole view
will dissolve and how how much it
doesn't add up because the sutas are
completely unambiguous about it when the
Buddha talked to lay people when he was
telling how to look after the wives or
Kings how to rule the it was nothing to
do with freedom from Nana Noble aath and
the DH sorry freedom from from samsara
Nana and and and the dhama it was for
the Heavenly rebirths for the better
life here and now it was because they
clearly did want to practice so he would
not have wasted the practice instruction
that would have been misunderstood and
misconstrued to somebody not even
willing to hear it and when those lay
people did were
instructed it was exactly on the same
basis as the monks
were yeah there's the keep the keep the
five precepts you'll go to heaven yeah
you'll enjoy cental Pleasures there
exactly but then there's the danger of
those essential tases yeah and see
there's absolutely nothing wrong with
that that's the
point that becomes a
seriously mistaken and perilous position
when for whatever reason that became
understood as the practice of the Dharma
as well okay and that's just delusional
as I
said but it's but it's the idea that the
virtue is not even the five precepts is
not important but the meditation
is that is even worse because well yeah
it's completely upside down because even
if you keep the five precepts and you're
aiming for the
heavens still you are you are in a way
practicing the good path well you're not
drifting away too far away from the
starting point you're not practicing the
path but as I said before by keeping the
five prets which is the Buddha said the
bare minimum you at least as I said not
too far off so where you do take the
precepts or start to practice sense
restraint or reflect on these right
correct context and so on you are
actually close to where things would be
starting but if you're not even keeping
the five precepts and just doing some
meditation or occasionally keeping the
precepts when when you're on the retreat
that's as I said you can do whatever you
want to manage your suffering and it's
it's absolutely fine there's really no
problem the problem is when all those
absolutely worldly misguided in terms of
the Dharma managements are seen as the
practice of the Dharma that's the the
worst thing you can do
really that's even worse than somebody
who is making no effort to practice but
at least is not obscuring what the
practice actually
is and when you when you what relegate
virtue as being unimportant that
meditation inside meditation experiences
is being the core then if you're a monk
then or late person it means you know
what's the point of being monastic it's
absolutely well in a way yeah exactly
exactly then anybody if the practice
everybody has access to the practice
through a meditation technique
everything else secondary to it yeah but
you know it's obviously it's like the
mainstream view most people do it and
most people say well but I find it
helpful nobody doubts that nobody denies
that but you need to really start looking
but you need to really start looking
into where the whole thing came from
because you're not going to find it in
the sutas and whenever people some say
it comes from this sutas it's always
quite a quite a
leap to to make those connections and
then people would sometimes just just
accept it that he came from the sutas
because he was presented the sutas were
presented to them through these
meditation techniques and they haven't
really looked into them and studied them
for themselves but there were there were
books written on the whole origins of
the like modern genre views and stuff um
maybe we can even link them like a
couple of like like full-on Scholastic
Books not just somebody expressing The
View like like I'm doing now and then
quote the sutas which as I said are
fairly generic people can interpret them
whichever way they want no this was like
a like a scholarly research on the basis
of other research of other research full
on like investigative work where just
there's no doubt like even people that
practice the the Buddha ghost J method
and whatnot that had nothing to do with
the Buddhist Jas actually even those
Scholars know that that didn't come from
the sutas they just accept and like and
and think budos knew what he was talking
about um but uh there is absolutely no
disagreement that that has come like oh
10 centuries later 6 11 and by that time
there was a lot already like three
centuries after the Buddha passed away
it was already you know by the time
those s councils were coming it was
already different different T yogic
influences and and whatnot so it's just
to show you that okay you can do
whatever you want but if you want to
claim it to be the dharm and the
practice for theing of the suffering and
so on you need to go back to the sutas
that as I said there is quite a wide
consensus the early texts what they were
and really study them on their own Merit
not like interpret them through your own
as I said
you know breath massage tantric
technique and try to read into it no no
just look what it says forget what you
know and what's the first thing that
come to your mind when you read Anan
well the first thing that come to my
mind is he wasn't t to
householders the second thing that come
to my mind he was taught to people with
the right view or with at least fully
established virt sense restraint like
Beyond any doubt so it's like you want
to get in these other subsequent
technicalities of Jana of of anapana
Sati steps well you got to meet these
technicalities first is my life
approximating that of a fully
established in virtue cacy sense
restraint whereby I could say well it
does apply to me or no again you could
say oh well my teacher told me he
doesn't have to well we not talking
about your teacher we talking about the
early Buddhist text the sutas that are
as I said wildely agreed okay this is
the closest to the what bud actually
thought and most likely it was from the
historical figure that did teach these
things do those texts allow you to be a
householders with occasional five
precept doing higher Sati panas and
anapanasati and for
Jana not a chance by any
stretch and now you have a choice again
you could say okay I don't like this I
do prefer my My Le J teacher and I'll
follow him that's fine but you were told
and there is plenty of evidence to even
prove that point Scholastic in
investigative works and stuff that those
are two different
things because I I was I would see
sometimes people CL oh well this is the
Buddha J and then there is this J this A
J is like well no there is J full stop
there is no 16 types of J all the
subsequent janas are the ones that fail
to understand or attain the Buddhist J
the J from the early texts otherwise you
wouldn't come up with your own practice
of
Jan so it's it's simply not optional and
if the choice is clear as I said before
in other talks you might even surprise
yourself you you think now maybe you
think oh it's just too much to do all
that and once you're clear once you calm
down in your initial shock because you
know for 20 years you've been doing it
this way you might surprise yourself and
realize actually I am kind of doing it
like this rightly now I don't I don't
have actually problem with the sensor
strain as much as I thought I did I
could even do it more I could even do it
more occasionally I take on the pr let
me take it on for longer let me now
uh improve like the the restraint and
the practice in regard to the the speech
the action revolv on speech oh let me
now like nand mat purify thoughts in
their manifestation without relying on any
manifestation without relying on any
management technique just as they arise
I see through them again she was a lay
woman with probably lots of Duties and
stuff and pressures and she did all of
that so it's like if as a householder
you can become an anagami that's a
pretty good deal but but again the
practice is the same and that's another
thing you could like okay so could you
become anagami somebody who is fully
utterly completely destroyed the five
fetes it's above sensuality or real will
while practicing sexual
activity like put put everything put all
the text aside all the teachings just
use Clear reason just pure logic
straightforward reflection and see can
you do this and get this as a result of
that and see if that's just wishful
thinking and a complete kind of as I
said um misled belief because it's
impossible by any stretch if you just
stop and think about it you realize no
of course if I want to be Beyond
sensuality I have to start emulating
that I have to start not giving into it
it's like a heroin addict through
shooting up
drugs genuinely
believes if he were to genuinely believe
that he will go beyond his addiction
through feeding it every single day he
will go beyond it
and you don't even need to become a
heroin addict to realize that that's not
how sensuality
works and somehow you do have views of I
can just keep the five precepts the best
I can and practice for anagami the
destruction and I find this secret
pleasure hidden in the Jan they will
then make me abandon the whole
sensuality and never look back
again and again you look at the actual
sutas and it's it's a very different
picture painted
there you can't get get the pleasure of
renunciation by not by not not rcing
yeah so in a way it's actually like I'm
just imagining like if I were uh if I
were a household and somebody tells me
this it's like well
actually that's kind of
better I don't have to be relying on the
magic of techniques and attainments I
had a special experience a what does it
mean and stuff that and then depend on
someone else's
word keep the five precepts keep the
eight when you can do it as often as you
can uh moderate your engagement and
compromise of sensuality and other
things and then you have plenty of
opportunities for
practice people will be provoking you to
say stuff to think stuff and you realize
every single day you're served on a
plate things that can directly lead to
Improvement of your chitt or defilement
it but you got to do the work and it's
like yeah actually it's quite reasonable
if somebody takes on that kind of work
even if it's five occasional eight five
occasional eight but does all of this
does not mask or manage through
techniques and and mystical experiences
and hypnotic transes yes there is a good
chance you could get the r view or at
least be like on the level of a damari
and then get the right view at the
moment of death or something your mind
will be very clean well the mind the
mind is actually being worked properly
as opposed to just hypnotized distracted
enticed with more sensuality to look
away from this sensuality no no no you
taking it on rightly yes you're not
going to be an Arun but being a soop
it's you know as would said himself in
those suas it's worth being what is it
like stuck by 100 Spears every day for
100 years if at the end of that you to get
years if at the end of that you to get
the soop part it would be worth going
through that
pain so nothing stopping you really
nothing stopping anyone except their
wrong views and and mistaken misplaced
emphasis on what really the practice is
and what's
important because although that that's
difficult and it's painful a wise person
would see that
this pain is worth this pain is the
practice Yeah is the practice because
look at the results would be Clarity of
Mind steadiness of heart so to speak y
Taming of the animal and as a lay person
if you are still attached to your family
and and concerned with your children
wife wouldn't it be best if you you had
a clean mind clean Behavior Uh non non
non- clouded perspective in regard to
what's better would that not Inspire
your own family wouldn't you be teaching
your children the right right way to
live if you're beyond ill will beyond
the best thing that you should be doing
for your family and it's also good in
other ways obviously I usually don't
talk about that because generally it's
for like a wide audience but the Buddha
said himself uh offering feeding helping a
himself uh offering feeding helping a
virtuous person will be like
immeasurable Merit offering feeding
helping a soana even more Sak even more
anagami even
AR so if you yourself are actually the
one with develop CH as a householder
developed CH developed virtue on the way
for the Right View damari sari
committing to it rightly anything good
your wife kids friends do to you will be
multiplied by thousandfold for them in
terms of because there's the whole suit
that talks about purification of gifts
and offerings through virtue of the
receiver virtue of The Giver or
both and it's like you are practicing
for the benefit animals they do
something good for you if you are one
with a purifi CH they're going to reap
manifold benefit from that if you were
not probably not going to last for long
so it's it's beneficial one way or the
other
yeah you are becoming and that's what I
mean like and all this is in the
Sur you you read this like actually that
is perfectly
doable because yes many people would
have valid reasons you know already have
you know a growing family or people that
depend on them you know maybe not as
much as Back in the Day in India where
you would leave your family means okay
they're done but still there is degree
of responsibility and involvement and
they can't just now it's too late so to
speak it's too late to just give it us
and become a monk because all of this
but it's like okay but it's not too late
to internally start walking in the right
direction on the basis of that
compromised environment take on that
pain of Untamed J being faced correctly
T it through virtue five precepts they
keep you not drifting away from the
practice eight precepts they align you
more with the practice the right
Reflections even the reflections on your
own family see you are your children are
your bond
what happens to bonds what happens to
those who are bonded well make your
meditation around that every other day
one day think about the The Virtue the
value of Enlightenment the value of
immovable CH another day think about the
paddles of sensuality sure engage with
sensuality when you have to as I said in
a moderate way but that still doesn't
exempt you from thinking how bad it is
think about the danger of the bond think
about your children dying before
you would your mind remain IM moved like
nand Matas
did it's like oh you wouldn't so I got
to work towards that I and you don't
need to abandon children in order to do
their work so there's no excuse to not
do the work that's my point even if you
say I can't become a monk okay still
have to do the same
work I can't become celebrate because I
have duty to his wife okay fine still
think those same themes contexts and
contemplations they will keep in but
it's going to be unpleasant because
obviously you in them and thinking them
it's like but that is your training
there if you abandon that and become a
monk as in that environment and become
monk you're going to have different
types of unpleasantness to think about
but one way or the other it has to come
because we all start with an untame
chitt we all start with a wild animal
that does need to be rained in and then
fed these perceptions as the suta says
kept in front of it until it sees for
itself